In this section I'm going to give you a basic introduction of vectors, embeddings, vector database
and search. So why do we need vectors? So now let's say I go to a shopping mall and I purchase
some books and Apple. Now I have to know what is the price of these books. So it's a simple
problem to solve. I can build an application and then have a relational database like my SQL,
where I store the price of these books and Apple and then I just square it and I get the
results. But now let's assume that I was watching Instagram and I really like this watch
but I want it in the blue color. So how do I do the image search to find the right watch?
Now another scenario is let's say I build an e-learning app for my organization and I have a PDF
in the backend which talks about the best practices of building a rag-based application.
Now let's say my learner poses a question which is the most cost effective vector database
in Amazon, bedrock. Now how does my generative application actually
search this PDF to answer that question? It cannot do a keyword search but it has to do
semantic search. So what semantic search means that it will try and understand the user question
and then generate an answer. So to solve these kind of problems, image search,
searching the unstructured data we use vectors. Now let's try and understand how.
So the first thing is what are vectors? So vectors are mathematical representation of words,
sentences and documents. So vectors are represented by list of numbers or sequence of numbers.
Okay so this is a lot of words let's try and understand what it means. Now if I want to
represent this word apple in vector terms, so what I can say is I can have two attributes,
I can say is it a fruit if it's yes then I say one and what is the cost of this apple four dollars.
Now I can represent the word apple as one comma four from these two values and then I can plot it
on a two dimensional graph. So I say on the way axis is it a fruit one so it's here
then on the x dimension I have cost it's four so this is how I can represent word apple on a
two dimensional chart. Then maybe I have word banana so I can say is it a fruit yes one and then
cost is two dollars. So I represent it in the vector form as one comma two and then if I plot it
on the chart so two and so it's a fruit so it's here and then two dollars so it's here.
So now what we have done is we have created the vector representation of these words in two
dimensions but in the real world you actually create this representation in 512 to 1024
dimension. So basically here we just have two dimension but in real world we can have 512
seconds of numbers to represent maybe a word sentence or even a document. Okay now to continue
on the previous use case where our user has posed a question and we have the user guide of bedrock
which is let's say 500 pages. So we can represent that as one vector as well but that's not
going to give us great results. So in most scenarios what you're going to do is you're going to
split that data or sometimes called as data chunking and you can do that based on character token
or code. So let's try and assume that we are going to do it by character. So what you're going to do
is so for a 500 page document you're going to break it into one page each and then one page each
you're going to break into paragraphs and then you're going to break it into characters. So maybe
120 characters or 200 characters. So how do you do that? So there are a lot of open source frameworks
like line chain which provides libraries to do this split. So once you do the split you pass it
through an embedding model. So now what is an embedding model? We'll discuss that.
Now let's say you split the document into 120 characters each then you will pass it through embedding
model. So there are a lot of different embedding models available in Amazon bedrock. So you have from
Amazon Titan, you have from Kohir and so on. So once you pass these 120 characters that you have
split through an embedding model you will create something known as vector embeddings. And as I said
they are between 512 to 1024 dimensions and here you can see an example you had passed maybe
just a single word, great or you can also pass a sentence, what is the price of an apple,
maybe entire document. So once you pass it through the embedding model so you'll get a vector embedding
and it will be of 1024 dimensions. Next we have the vector store. So now let's say you are split
the document into multiple chunks you passed it through a embedding model and then now you have
different vector embeddings here of 1024 dimensions each. Now you have to store all of these
vector embeddings somewhere and that's where vector store comes into play. So AWS provides multiple
options on the vector store or vector DB such as AWS open search pine cone and so on and we're going
to discuss those later. Okay now once you have stored all these vector embeddings so what's the use
now let's see. So now let's say we have this pine cone vector DB and now we have passed the entire
document after splitting into 120 characters each. So maybe we have hundreds and thousands of
vector embeddings and now they have been stored here. Now what's going to happen is the end user
is going to pose a question. Let's say he poses which vector DB is most cost effective in AWS.
Now what my large language model needs to do is it needs to go ahead and the right vector embedding
that is stored in this vector DB which will have the contextual answer because remember we're split
the document into pages, Paris and then two or three lines based on where 120 characters would
and then all of them are scattered here. So it's going to search for the relevant chunk which
can answer this question. So how does it do that? So once we have the user question so it's going
to pass that through the embedding model and in this case we're just using Amazon Titan embedding
model. So once it passes through the embedding model it's going to create a vector embedding and
then it's going to do something known as similarity search. So basically it will check for a very
similar vector embedding that can answer the user question. So once it does the similarity search
it's going to retrieve anywhere between 5 to 20 chunks based on how you are connected to the solution
and then it's going to return those chunks to the large language model which will then
generate an answer for the user question. Now how does the similarity search happen? So similarity
search is done through two algorithms sometimes known as K nearest neighbor algorithm or approximate
nearest neighbor. So KNN or K nearest neighbor algorithm is a supervised machine learning algorithm
that can be used for classification and regression tasks. So if you're interested in knowing
more about KNN or ANN let me know send me an email and I can add one lecture towards the end
of this course. Now you don't need to get into details of how the KNN or ANN algorithm works
because it is done behind the scenes by AWS but if you are still interested send me an email
I will add one lecture which explain how the similarity search works at the end of the course.
Okay so that's pretty much it from this lecture I will send the next lecture. Thank you.